<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Collective Logic Lab - News</title><link href="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/feeds/news.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/</id><updated>2025-04-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Diya Hamada successfully defends undergraduate honors thesis</title><link href="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/diya-hamada-successfully-defends-undergraduate-honors-thesis.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-04-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-04-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Bryan Daniels</name></author><id>tag:www.public.asu.edu,2025-04-25:/~bdaniel6/cll/diya-hamada-successfully-defends-undergraduate-honors-thesis.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to Diya Hamada for successfully defending their undergraduate honors thesis, "Predicting Honey Bee Foraging: Recent Dance Floor Visit Outweighs Age and Temporal Cues"!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="News"></category></entry><entry><title>Our study on bistability in the gene expression of honey bees is published</title><link href="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/our-study-on-bistability-in-the-gene-expression-of-honey-bees-is-published.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-10-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Bryan Daniels</name></author><id>tag:www.public.asu.edu,2023-10-26:/~bdaniel6/cll/our-study-on-bistability-in-the-gene-expression-of-honey-bees-is-published.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Finding critical transitions in gene expression time series&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In development, cells in an embryo start out all having the same DNA and similar behavior. As …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Finding critical transitions in gene expression time series&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In development, cells in an embryo start out all having the same DNA and similar behavior. As the cells grow and divide, they eventually take on distinct identities.  The fact that there exist separate identities ("cell types") and not just a continuum of possible behaviors can be explained by nonlinearities in the dynamics of gene regulation.  The identities correspond to distinct jobs that the cells have in supporting the functions of the entire organism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, in honey bee colonies, individual bees start their lives all performing the same behaviors within the nest.  In the course of aging and in response to cues from the environment, each bee will eventually transition to a different bee "type" that goes outside the nest to find food.  This transition is visible not just in the bees' behavior but at the level of genes expressed by each bee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More generally, a transition from one type of behavior into two separate types connects with ideas of bifurcations in dynamical systems or phase transitions in statistical physics.  Using mathematical tools from these fields, we can find the specific shape of the probability distributions expected near such transitions.  This allows us to more easily search for such transitions in gene expression data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we successfully found the transition from in-hive to foraging behavior in bees by looking for the transition from monostability to bistability in gene expression data.  We could do this even with a relatively small amount of data: just 16 bees per timepoint.  We also show that it beats other standard methods like Gaussian mixture models because it uses the shape of the transition known from Landau theory in statistical physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future, our method could be used as a precise and efficient way to search for critical transitions in high-dimensional data across many examples, from cell development to neuroscience to social systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to my wonderful collaborators on this project: Rob Page, Ying Wang, and Gro Amdam!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for more details in our writeup in PLoS Computational Biology: &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1010704"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1010704&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="News"></category></entry><entry><title>Our new paper on criticality in fish schools is published</title><link href="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/our-new-paper-on-criticality-in-fish-schools-is-published.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-06-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Bryan Daniels</name></author><id>tag:www.public.asu.edu,2022-06-22:/~bdaniel6/cll/our-new-paper-on-criticality-in-fish-schools-is-published.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Limiting the viral spread of information in fish schools&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When one animal's behavior influences the behavior of its neighbors, changes can quickly spread through a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Limiting the viral spread of information in fish schools&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When one animal's behavior influences the behavior of its neighbors, changes can quickly spread through a group. Theory predicts that information spreads most easily when the strength of this influence is close to a critical value.  Many living systems, from neurons in brains to birds in a flock, appear to be tuned near this special value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To look for this phenomenon in fish schools, we studied the spreading of startling behavior, which helps fish escape from predators.  Surprisingly, we found that the schools are far from optimal in transmitting information across the school.  Instead, fish limit this behavioral spreading, likely because it helps to ignore false alarms. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This behavior of fish may inspire us to think differently about other living systems, including our own human social networks: How can we balance potential drawbacks against the benefits of easy viral spreading of information and ideas?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A shout out goes to Winnie Poel, the recent PhD graduate who (tirelessly and meticulously) did most of the work on this project, as well as my other wonderful fish and collective behavior collaborators who worked on this: Matt Sosna, Colin Twomey, Simon Leblanc, Iain Couzin, and Pawel Romanczuk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the details in Science Advances: &lt;a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.abm6385"&gt;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.abm6385&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="News"></category></entry><entry><title>Our new paper on collective neural control is published</title><link href="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/our-new-paper-on-collective-neural-control-is-published.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-06-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Bryan Daniels</name></author><id>tag:www.public.asu.edu,2022-06-06:/~bdaniel6/cll/our-new-paper-on-collective-neural-control-is-published.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;New technology can manipulate the brain activity of small worms, potentially allowing for control of behavior through the nudging of neurons.  But it is difficult …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;New technology can manipulate the brain activity of small worms, potentially allowing for control of behavior through the nudging of neurons.  But it is difficult to predict which nudges will work best: Even in the simple brain of a worm, many individual neurons do not have a single well-defined role.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a project spearheaded by Eddie Lee, with help from our collaborator Xiaowen Chen, we envision new types of experiments that could efficiently find the best sets of neurons to manipulate for any desired effect.  We explore the ways in which neural activity and its control over behavior can remain low-dimensional — our findings suggest that only a few aspects of neural activity matter for controlling what a worm does, and these changes can be made by nudging only a small number of neurons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the details in Plos Computational Biology: &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1010072"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1010072&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="News"></category></entry><entry><title>Our work on collective behavior highlighted in Harper's</title><link href="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/our-work-on-collective-behavior-highlighted-in-harpers.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-03-14T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-03-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Bryan Daniels</name></author><id>tag:www.public.asu.edu,2022-03-14:/~bdaniel6/cll/our-work-on-collective-behavior-highlighted-in-harpers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was already thrilled to see a piece in Harper's on collective animal behavior, complete with gorgeous photos of synchronizing ...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="a magazine article" src="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/images/article.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steven Strogatz ... believes that the world's outstanding scientific mysteries, regardless of discipline, are all questions of collectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was already thrilled to see a piece in Harper's on collective animal behavior, complete with gorgeous photos of synchronizing fireflies.  I was even more excited to see our research mentioned, in the context of startle behavior spreading through fish schools (joint with Winnie Poel, Matt Sosna, Pawel Romanczuk, Iain Couzin, and others).  But to see Steve Strogatz, one of my scientific heroes, paraphrased to highlight "collectives" as &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; scientific subject of our times — I was amazed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not often that science journalism captures my imagination when covering science that I am so close to.  Vanessa Gregory did a great job grounding our sometimes very abstract area of research in an understandable and compelling way without watering it down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the article here: &lt;a href="https://harpers.org/archive/2022/03/bright-flight-fireflies-collective-behavior-blink/"&gt;harpers.org/archive/2022/03/bright-flight-fireflies-collective-behavior-blink/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="News"></category></entry></feed>