<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Collective Logic Lab - Research Musings</title><link href="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/feeds/research-musings.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/</id><updated>2023-06-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Abandoned Ideas File</title><link href="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/abandoned-ideas-file.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Bryan Daniels</name></author><id>tag:www.public.asu.edu,2023-05-22:/~bdaniel6/cll/abandoned-ideas-file.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Moving along in academia leaves a path littered with unfollowed leads.  I open my dusty file of abandoned ideas and release them into the wild...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Moving along in academia can feel like a gradual transition from the (undergraduate / graduate) hunger for important questions to tackle, to the (graduate / postdoc) satiation of producing good questions and tackling them, to the (postdoc / professor) overabundance of producing more questions than you know what to do with.  Even offloading questions to students leaves a path littered with unfollowed leads.  As I enter a busier phase of my career, I want to open my dusty file of abandoned ideas and release them into the wild...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abandoned idea #130715&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cultural evolution of popular colors.  Preliminary analysis: Over-represented colors on the covers of yearly top 10 music albums across decades.  What is the rate of change in color space?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="popular colors over decades" src="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/images/album image overrepresented colors by decade.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abandoned idea #131101&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the fact that Newton's laws are described in terms of positions and their derivatives connected to the fact that there is a minimum embedding dimension, implying there could be equivalent descriptions in terms of other variables?  Inspired by Packard, Crutchfield, Farmer, Shaw (1980).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abandoned idea #160406&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the 2nd Law of Thermodynamics equivalent to the Data Processing Inequality?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abandoned idea #170421&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I'm counting the number of memories that can be stored in a Hopfield network, how does that correspond to human memories? Experiencing a memory tends to be more associative, flowing from one idea to another. It's not as if I fall into one discrete holistic memory state and that's that. How would I count the number of memories I have?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abandoned idea #201022&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auto-correct could be making communication less reliable. When it works, it makes communication perhaps faster (the receiver doesn't have to make the correction themselves), but no more precise (the receiver can correct errors just as well as the computer). But when it doesn't work, it hinders precision because it's harder for the receiver to decode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abandoned idea #121210&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Galois theory seems to be providing the conditions under which there are no "shortcuts" to solving a polynomial equation (so you have to resort to doing it numerically—guess and check) in terms of group theory (non-decomposable groups and such). Related to NP hard problems?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Research Musings"></category></entry><entry><title>A Dream</title><link href="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/a-dream.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-06-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Bryan Daniels</name></author><id>tag:www.public.asu.edu,2018-06-15:/~bdaniel6/cll/a-dream.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Disheartened, you sit alone in a darkened lab, staring at a glowing laptop.  Signals pulse along a simulated network on the screen.
You have spent …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Disheartened, you sit alone in a darkened lab, staring at a glowing laptop.  Signals pulse along a simulated network on the screen.
You have spent the last three months painstakingly building a simulation of a complicated cellular process, the pathway leading from
insulin detected at surface of a cell to changes to its metabolic functions.
Now you have hit another bug: after correcting one parameter value, the simulation is again doing something miserably wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You let your mind wander, looking down at your hands, thinking about the cells in your own
body.  Somehow, right there in front of you, the jumble of biochemical reactions you have been trying to understand is mindlessly churning away, transforming
signals received by each cell into appropriate responses.  But the workings remain hazy and mysterious, involving so
many interacting parts that even your simplified simulation has a baroque character reminiscent of Rube Goldberg.  It seems amazing that such
precisely adapted, robust behavior can be the result of dynamics distributed over this mess of a network. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have lighting fast access to a database chock full of data.  You have the latest
machine learning software and access to a giant computing cluster in the cloud.  Yet in your late-night funk 
the problem seems insurmountable: 
Even once you have fixed this bug to get the simulation behaving in the right way, how do you understand how
the collective actually functions as a whole?  You have been working on this for months, and still you can barely keep the 
entire system in your head at once.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sighing, you let your head fall to the keyboard.  Maybe a quick rest...   You nod off, imagining the biochemical soup as a computer in disguise,
transforming inputs like insulin levels into the expression of particular genes.  Like neurons transforming
sensory input into coordinated motor
output; like a flock of birds amplifying the detection of a predator.  How do we understand the logic of these distributed computers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You jolt awake as someone taps you on the head.  You look up into a spooky mirror image of your own face, with a few more wrinkles and grey hairs—a faithful copy of yourself, aged ten or fifteen years.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The face smiles.  "Don't panic.  I come from a future time, when technological and conceptual advances are moving us toward
answering your questions.  I thought you might need some inspiration."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are handed a thick sheet of paper impossibly active with appearing and disappearing inky designs. 
A slider interface at the edge of the page is the only static element.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Here's an old USB adapter—give it some data." Dumbfounded, you plug the USB stick into your laptop and upload a few thousand measurements of the biochemical state of cells, each measuring hundreds of types of proteins and genes. 
A white LED blinks.  The paper refreshes to display "Auto-inferrer," and you tap to confirm: "System input: insulin concentration. 
System output: glucose concentration.  System type: protein interaction network."  A progress bar appears and marches quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"This should be quick with such a small amount of data."  Your doppelgänger winks at you.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A detailed network representation appears—you guess there is one node for each of the hundreds of measured proteins.  You see the resemblance, but it is more refined than the handmade version on your primitive looking laptop screen.  The nodes pulse with colored ink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"It's demonstrating now that the model can reconstruct the data you fed it. 
You haven't measured every protein species in the cell, so of course the connections you see are effective, phenomenological.&lt;br&gt;
But you can predict the effect of perturbations." 
Your twin reaches down and presses on one of the nodes, and it gradually darkens, 
affecting in subtle ways the broader network patterns.  "But that's just for show.  Here's the real magic."
Your future self holds up the sheet and points at the slide bar running up the page.  "Try it."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You nudge the slider up a bit.  The network bubbles and distorts, forming a column of three large circles connected by thick arrows.  The original
nodes are faintly visible inside each circle.
"Aha, a simpler representation!"  Of course! you think.  You had been on the verge of hypothesizing this yourself:
basically, the genes separate into three modules that form a cascade to transmit the signal.  Your double's finger points at a statistic written
to the side: "You can see that this simplified version still captures 90 percent of the variance in the input-output mapping."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Automated dimensionality reduction!
Impressed, you excitedly push the slider all the way to the top.  The network disappears, replaced by a plain-looking plot.
"The plot shows a single curve that branches into two.  As the simulation progresses, a dot marches from the single curve side to fall onto one of the two curves on the right.
"Looks like you've got a symmetry breaking circuit."  Pressing on the upper curve produces a representation of the three-state 
system with the final group active, and the lower curve shows it inactive.  "Oh, it's beautiful!" you exclaim.  "The two stable output
states arise from a bifurcation—and we can immediately see how they correspond to aggregate states of the individual genes!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your new friend smiles and continues to show off what the gadget can do on more complicated datasets. 
Using behavioral data from a fish school, the abstract setting shows a critical instability and demonstrates how information 
about predators is maximized when the school is closer to the instability.
Using measurements from millions of simultaneously measured neurons, you see the neurons grouped into functional clusters that create an aggregate level gated sensory classifier.
Using insulin expression 
and other cell-phone measured health data consisting of a few noisy data points for each of millions of patients produces patient-specific 
predictions and proposes the existence of important unmeasured variables at the most detailed setting, blames 
oscillatory dynamics on a Hopf bifurcation at the abstract setting, and suggests perturbations that promote or inhibit the oscillations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your friend is on a roll: 
"And you see how this combination of statistical inference and model selection can start to answer questions about what these 
distributed systems are doing and how they work?  How we are able to look both at the individual scale dynamics and the aggregate scale logic?
We quickly extract in each case how individual components control the behavior of the whole. 
We begin to understand what is carefully tuned and what is compensated for through 
active adjustment—the feedback that allows collective systems to remain adaptive and informative!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You inspect the front and back of the paper-thin sheet and get caught up in the excitement.  You stutter, "But—how does this work?"&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Research Musings"></category></entry><entry><title>Collective Behavior: Amplification</title><link href="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/collective-behavior-amplification.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-02-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Bryan Daniels</name></author><id>tag:www.public.asu.edu,2016-02-02:/~bdaniel6/cll/collective-behavior-amplification.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;How do little things combine to do big things? Collective behavior in living systems is fascinating and diverse: proteins collectively perform metabolism in your cells ...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="collective amplification" src="https://www.public.asu.edu/~bdaniel6/cll/images/amplification.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do little things combine to do big things?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collective behavior in living systems is fascinating and diverse: proteins collectively perform metabolism in your cells; neurons collectively process information in your brain; honeybees collectively forage and care for their young.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collective behavior in inanimate systems is also beautiful and can be more pristine: the fact that the atoms of carbon in a diamond are equivalent means that the crystal structure they form can be utterly precise.  It also makes it easier to describe real crystals and predict their properties: once you know the fundamental repeating building block, it's just a matter of scaling up to have trillions of repeating units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physics tells us a lot about how to deal with these less complicated collective systems.  We can connect the properties of atoms to the properties of familiar objects, like the hardness of a diamond.  Can this expertise be ported to biological examples, where individuals are not so simple?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One connection we've been thinking about involves how information is amplified in producing a system's aggregate behavior.  As an example of a system with low amplification, imagine our diamond under usual conditions: if we somehow jostled just a few atoms, this wouldn't have a huge effect.  The jostling would quickly dissipate without changing the overall structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many living systems, though, changes to individuals can have a large effect on the whole.  A single bird might change the direction of a flock; a change to the activity of a few neurons might affect your subsequent behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can quantify this "amplification" with a fundamental measure from information theory—the Fisher information—which also turns out to have interesting connections to the idea of a phase transition in statistical physics.  It's also a natural measure from the point of view of biology:  Amplifying important information and damping extraneous noise can be key to the survival of a group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this way, amplification measures a fundamental property of collectives, one that could be compared across different systems.  Making the connection to statistical physics, we might ask questions like, "How far is this fish school from a phase transition?"  Making the connection to biology, we might ask, "How is the correct information from individuals amplified to influence the behavior of the whole?"  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through this lens of amplification and others that describe distinct aspects of information processing, we aim eventually to map out the space of strategies used by living systems as they combine to form functional aggregates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Research Musings"></category></entry></feed>